Aline and Eero Saarinen
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Aline and Eero Saarinen papers
1906-1977
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Saarinen, Aline Bernstein
13.5 linear feet
The Aline and Eero Saarinen papers measure approximately 13.5 linear feet and date from 1906 to 1977. The bulk of the collection consists of Aline Saarinen's papers which document her relationship with her husband Eero Saarinen and other aspects of their personal lives, as well as Aline's work as an art and architectural critic, author, and television correspondent. Papers include research files for published and planned books (in which can be found scattered original letters of Stanford White, John Quinn and Edward Root) and other projects, NBC correspondent files, writings, committee files, correspondence, photographs, printed material, and miscellaneous personal papers.
Biographical Note
Aline Bernstein Saarinen was born on March 25, 1914 in New York City. She attended Vassar College, where she took art courses and became interested in journalism, and graduated with a B.A. in 1935. She went on to receive her M.A. in the history of architecture from the Institute of Fine Arts at New York University in 1941. She married Joseph H. Louchheim in 1935, and they had two sons, Donald and Harry (or Hal). They divorced in 1951.
Aline joined the staff of Art News Magazine in 1944 and served as managing editor from 1946 to 1948. She edited and provided commentary for the book, 5000 Years of Art in Western Civilization, which was published in 1946. She served as associate art editor and critic at The New York Times from 1948 to 1953 and then as associate art critic from 1954 to 1959. She received awards for her newspaper work, including the International Award for Best Foreign Criticism at the Venice Biennale in 1951, the Frank Jewett Mather Award for best newspaper art criticism in 1953, and the American Federation of Arts Award for best newspaper criticism in 1956.
In 1953, Aline interviewed the architect Eero Saarinen for an article. Eero was born in 1910 in Kirkkonummi, Finland, and received his B.F.A. in Architecture from Yale University in 1934. He began work as an architect in his father Eliel Saarinen's firm and went on to start his own firm, Eero Saarinen and Associates. Among his best-known works are the Gateway Arch in St. Louis, Missouri, the Trans World Air Lines Terminal Building at John F. Kennedy Airport in New York, and Dulles International Airport in Chantilly, Virginia.
Aline and Eero became romantically involved shortly after they met and were married in December 1953. The following year, they had a son, Eames (named after Eero's friend, the designer and architect Charles Eames). After their marriage, Aline relocated to Bloomfield Hills, Michigan, where she continued to work as associate art critic for The New York Times and where she served as Director of Information Service in the office of Eero Saarinen and Associates (from 1954 to 1963).
In 1957, she received a Guggenheim Fellowship to work on a book about major American art collectors, The Proud Possessors, which was published by Random House in 1958. Thereafter, she began work on a biography of the architect, Stanford White, also for Random House; this work continued for several years, but the book was never completed. Over the years, she wrote numerous freelance articles on art, architecture, socio-cultural history, travel, and theater for magazines such as Atlantic Monthly, Vogue, Saturday Review of Literature, Reader's Digest, and Cosmopolitan.
After Eero's sudden death in 1961, Aline edited the book, Eero Saarinen on His Work (1962). She then embarked upon a new career in television, appearing on shows such as "Today" and "Sunday" where she reported on manners, morals, culture, and the arts, and eventually becoming, in 1964, an NBC News correspondent for such shows as "The Huntley-Brinkley Report" and "The Frank McGee Report" in addition to the shows on which she was already appearing. In 1971, she was appointed chief of the NBC News Paris Bureau, becoming the first woman to hold such a position in television.
In the 1960s, Aline served on various arts-related committees, including the Design Advisory Committee of the Federal Aviation Administration, the Fine Arts Commission, and the New York State Council of the Arts. She received honorary degrees from the University of Michigan in 1964 and Russell Sage College in 1967.
Aline Saarinen died from a brain tumor on July 13, 1972.
This biographical notes draws from the one on Aline Bernstein Saarinen by Seymour Brody in Jewish Heroes and Heroines of America: 150 True Stories of American Jewish Heroism, and from the one on Eero Saarinen in the Guide to the Eero Saarinen Collection at Yale University Library.
Scope and Content Note
The Aline and Eero Saarinen papers measure approximately 13.5 linear feet and date from 1906 to 1977. The bulk of the collection consists of Aline Saarinen's papers which document her relationship with her husband Eero Saarinen and other aspects of their personal lives, as well as Aline's work as an art and architectural critic, author, and television correspondent. Papers include research files for published and planned books (in which can be found scattered original letters of Stanford White, John Quinn and Edward Root) and other projects, NBC correspondent files, writings, committee files, correspondence, photographs, printed material, and miscellaneous personal papers.
The portion of the collection relating to personal aspects of Aline and Eero Saarinen's lives consists of: Aline Saarinen's diary, guest book, notebooks, personal writings, biographical material, awards and honorary degrees; scattered papers of Eero Saarinen, including biographical material, drawings of furniture designs, various sketches and drawings, and some project timelines and notes; correspondence between Aline and Eero Saarinen (the bulk of which dates from the year they met and married), as well as general and family correspondence received by Aline Saarinen and some miscellaneous and personal correspondence of Eero Saarinen; printed material, mostly clippings, documenting aspects of the life, work, and achievements of both Aline and Eero Saarinen; and photographs, including ones of Aline Saarinen, Eero Saarinen, Aline and Eero Saarinen together, and family members, as well as ones from various trips and of various residences, and various slides.
The bulk of the collection consists of material, including research and writing files, NBC correspondent files, and committee files, stemming from Aline Saarinen's various professional activities. Writings include manuscripts, typescripts, notes, notecards, and clippings of Aline Saarinen's various articles, lectures and speeches on art and architecture, scripts for television, creative and college writing. Research files include material for Saarinen's published book on art collectors, The Proud Possessors, and her planned, but never completed, biography of the architect, Stanford White. Research material for The Proud Possessors includes files of notes, manuscripts, correspondence, photographs and printed material on art collectors, and related material such as scrapbooks of correspondence and clippings in response to the book. Files also include scattered original material, such as correspondence and photographs, belonging to the collectors, John Quinn and Edward Root. Research material on Stanford White includes correspondence, notebooks, writings, printed material, photographs, and copies of architectural drawings. Also found is scattered original material belonging to Bessie White, Stanford White, and the firm of McKim, Mead and White. NBC material consists of files, including correspondence, printed material, notes, scripts, motion picture films and video transfers, and photographs, kept by Aline Saarinen while working as a television correspondent. Also found are miscellaneous research files on artists that may relate to television or other projects and files stemming from her involvement in various arts-related and other committees.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series:
Series 1: Aline and Eero Saarinen Personal Papers, 1928-1977 (Boxes 1-4, 15, OV 16; 3.7 linear feet)
Series 2: Aline Saarinen Professional Papers, 1906-1969 (Boxes 4-15, OV 16; 9.8 linear feet)
Related Material
Also found in the Archives are: the Museum of Modern Art exhibition correspondence concerning Eero Saarinen, 1958-1959; the Lily Swann Saarinen papers, 1924-1974; an oral history interview with Lily Swann Saarinen, 1979-1981; and an oral history interview on Aline Saarinen with Charles Alan, 1973 February 17.
Other related material includes: Eero Saarinen Collection, Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library.
Separated Material
Two exhibition catalogs and various clippings that were donated as part of the collection were transferred to the Smithsonian American Art Museum Library in 1981.
Index Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following index terms. People, families and organizations are listed under "Subjects" when they are the topic of collection contents and under "Names" when they are creators or contributors.
Subjects:
Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961; White, Stanford, 1853-1906
Subjects-Topical:
Women architectural critics -- Michigan; Women art critics -- Michigan; Women art historians -- Michigan; Art -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Architecture -- United States; Architectural historians -- Michigan; Architects -- Michigan -- Bloomfield Hills
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Sound recordings; Interviews; Motion pictures (visual works)
Names:
Saarinen, Eero, 1910-1961
Provenance
The Aline and Eero Saarinen papers were donated in 1973 by Charles Alan, Aline Saarinen's brother and executor of her estate, and microfilmed. In 1966 five photographs of Eliel Saarinen's home in Helsinki, Finland were donated by Florence Davis and were subsequently integrated into the collection. The NBC material was donated in 1974 by NBC Studios via Charles Alan. Additional material, which had originally been donated to the Parrish Museum by Aline Saarinen, was donated to the Archives in 1991 by the Museum.
Restrictions on Access
The collection has been digitized and is available online via AAA's website. Use of material not digitized requires an appointment.
Alternative Forms Available
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2007 and is available via the Archives of American Art's website.
Material not scanned includes the NBC correspondent files (due to restrictions on the material), and typically duplicates, negatives, slides, and printed material easily accessible elsewhere. For publications found in the research and other project files, only relevant portions are scanned.
Location of Originals
The originals of the microfilmed correspondence of Richard Grant White and Stanford White found in Series 2.3.4 are located in the Huntington Art Library.
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Aline and Eero Saarinen Personal Papers, 1928-1977, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-4, 15, OV 16; 3.7 linear feet)
  Series consists of material relating to both Aline and Eero Saarinen, their relationship, their families, and other personal aspects of their lives. Most of the material found here was created and accumulated by Aline Saarinen. Also found is some material of Eero Saarinen's that was either created as part of their life together (such as photographs from various trips together) or that was later collected by Aline Saarinen as part of her own files (such as some drawings of Eero Saarinen's furniture designs).
  The Aline and Eero Saarinen Personal Papers series is arranged into four subseries:
  1.1: Miscellaneous Personal Papers, 1928-1974
  1.2: Correspondence, 1936-1970
  1.3: Printed Material, 1947-1977
  1.4: Photographs, 1940s-1970
  - Miscellaneous Personal Papers, 1943-1974, 1.1:
    Subseries consists primarily of material relating to personal aspects of Aline Saarinen's life, as well as some scattered papers of Eero Saarinen and a file relating to their son, Eames Saarinen.
    Aline Saarinen's papers include a diary she began as a young girl and periodically added to over the years; a guest book which records the names of people who visited her during the years 1961-1971, with gaps in-between; a notebook from a class she took with [Erwin] Panofsky on Baroque art in 1936; a notebook that she kept on the alterations to the first house that she and her first husband, Joseph Louchheim, purchased in 1949 (including diary entries, correspondence with architects and interior designers, photographs, estimates, and statements); her writing on the events surrounding almost being offered the Finnish Ambassadorship by President Lyndon B. Johnson in 1964; invitations and other material relating to various inaugural events during the 1960s; and some personal writings and biographical material. Also found are awards and honorary degrees, including an academic hood, received by Aline Saarinen (such as honorary degrees from University of Michigan and Russell Sage College), campaign buttons, press passes, and commemorative objects.
    Eero Saarinen's papers include biographical material (including a copy of his death certificate), some drawings of his furniture designs (mainly chairs), illustrated cards and certificates some of which were done with his son Eames, timelines and notes for various architectural projects, and various sketches and drawings, including sketches of Aline and himself, drawings of certain architectural projects with notes that he shared with Aline, various architectural sketches (some on the backs of placemats), and designs featuring their first initials, A and E.
    Papers relating to Eames Saarinen include correspondence to his mother, school reports, and some poems and other writings.
    Unless otherwise noted, the files relate to Aline Saarinen. Files are arranged alphabetically.
    - Art Work, Unidentified, undated, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1956-1967, (5 folders; see also Box 15; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 2-6)
    - Awards and Honorary Degrees, Academic Hood, 1960s, (See Box 15; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Biographical Material, 1943-1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Biographical Material, Eero Saarinen, 1961-1963, (Not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Campaign and Other Buttons, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Commemorative Objects, 1965, 1967, (Not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Diary, 1928-1939, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    - Dictabelts, undated, (2 folders; not scanned) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Drawings of Furniture Designs, Eero Saarinen, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Eames Saarinen, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Finnish Ambassadorship, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Guest Book, 1961-1971 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Illustrated Cards to Aline from Eero Saarinen, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Illustrated Certificates to G. Richard Davis from Eero Saarinen, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Inaugural and Other Events, 1961-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1956-1974, (2 folders; not scanned in entirety) (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
    - Notebook, "Panofsky's Course - Baroque", 1936, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 1-2)
    - Notebook on Joseph and Aline Louchheim's First House, Stamford, CT, 1948-1949, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-5)
    - Notes and Miscellany, 1950-1967 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Personal Writings, Aline and Eero Saarinen, 1950s, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
    - Press Passes, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Project Timelines and Miscellaneous Notes, Eero Saarinen, 1950s-1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Sketches and Drawings, Eero Saarinen, 1953-1961, (2 folders; see also OV 16) (Box 2, Folder 11-12)
    - Sketches of North Xian Church, Eero Saarinen, 1950s (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Sound Recording, Discussion on Sydney Opera House (Speakers: Eero Saarinen, H. Ingham Ashworth, and Leslie Martin), 1957 January 29, (See Box 15; not scanned) (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Oversize, Awards and Honorary Degrees, 1956-1967 (Box 15 (sol))
    - Oversize, Awards and Honorary Degrees, Academic Hood, 1960s (Box 15 (sol))
    - Oversize, Sound Recording, Discussion on Sydney Opera House (Speakers: Eero Saarinen, H. Ingham Ashworth, and Leslie Martin), 1957 January 29 (Box 15 (sol))
    - Oversize, Sketches and Drawings, Eero Saarinen, 1953-1961, (See Box 2, F11-12) (Box OV 16)
  - Correspondence, 1936-1970, 1.2:
    Subseries consists of correspondence between Aline and Eero Saarinen, general and family correspondence received by Aline Saarinen, and some miscellaneous correspondence received by Eero Saarinen. Also found are some personal letters of Eero Saarinen detailing the demise of his marriage to his first wife (Lily Swann Saarinen) which seem to have been written as part of undergoing psychotherapy and are addressed to his psychiatrist, "Dr. B", as well as a letter ending his relationship to a woman named Sampe, which may be a draft or a copy, though it is unclear whether the letter was ever actually sent.
    Correspondence between Aline and Eero Saarinen primarily dates from 1953, the year they met and married. Their correspondence documents the evolution of their relationship from time they met when Aline interviewed Eero for an article for The New York Times to Eero's divorce and their subsequent remarriage to each other. Also included are homemade birthday cards from Aline to Eero (of particular note is the one from 1953 which details the history of their romance). In addition to relationship matters, their correspondence typically concerns Aline's article on Eero, Eero's architectural projects (or as he puts it, "what goes on in my mind about work"), a forthcoming speech of his in Cleveland on which Aline assisted him, Aline's articles, Eero's divorce proceedings, their future plans, and sculpture for one of Eero's buildings. By and large, their correspondence from 1953 is undated according to month or day. Therefore, letters from that year are only arranged in rough chronological order.
    Aline Saarinen's general correspondence includes letters from friends, editors, her literary agent, lawyers, architects and designers, writers, government and university departments, political figures, and television producers, concerning articles, book ideas, dedication of Saarinen buildings, patents for Saarinen furniture designs, television shows, and committee work, among other matters. Correspondents include: Meyer Schapiro, Charles Eames, Louise Mendelsohn, Wayne Andrews, Hoke Norris, Hiram Haydn, Donald S. Klopfer, Bernice Cozzens, Lincoln Kirstein, The New York Times, James Gould Cozzens, J. Irwin Miller, Dwight D. Eisenhower (?), McCall's, Henry Dreyfuss, Lyndon B. Johnson, New York State Department, Russell Sage College, U.S. Department of Interior, Lady Bird Johnson, Nelson Rockefeller, and Wolf Von Eckhardt. General correspondence is typically arranged in chronological order. More extensive correspondence from Clifford Odets (which includes some drawings by Odets) and Frank Lloyd Wright (which concerns the Guggenheim Museum) is arranged into files according to correspondent.
    Eero Saarinen's miscellaneous correspondence includes copy of a letter to Huntington Hartford concerning the relationship between architecture and nature, and letters to and from S. Giedion regarding a plan for an International Exhibition of Modern Architecture, in addition to other scattered letters and the personal letters detailing his relationships with Lily and Sampe. Some or all of these letters may have been ones that Eero shared with Aline, which may be how they came to be amongst her papers.
    Family correspondence is comprised mainly of letters from Aline Saarinen's first husband, Joseph Louchheim, when he was working in Liberia for two months in 1949, and from her two sons from her first marriage, Donald and Hal Louchheim. Also found are individual letters from Eero's son from his first message, Eric and from their son, Eames.
    - Aline Saarinen to Eero Saarinen, 1953, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-21)
    - Aline Saarinen to Eero Saarinen, Birthday Card ("The Case-History of a Romance"), 1953 August 20 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Aline Saarinen to Eero Saarinen, Birthday Card, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Aline Saarinen to Eero Saarinen, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Aline Saarinen to Eero Saarinen, Miscellaneous, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Eero Saarinen to Aline Saarinen, 1953, (10 folders) (Box 2, Folder 26-35)
    - Eero Saarinen to Aline Saarinen, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Eero Saarinen to Donald and Hal Louchheim, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Aline Saarinen (Box 2)
      - General Correspondence, 1936-1937 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - General Correspondence, 1941-1948 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - General Correspondence, 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - General Correspondence, 1960-1963, (See also Box 15) (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - General Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 42)
      - General Correspondence, 1965-1971 (Box 2, Folder 43)
      - General Correspondence, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
      - General Correspondence - Odets, Clifford, 1952-1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      - General Correspondence - Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1953-1958 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Eero Saarinen (Box 2)
      - Letter to Sampe, circa 1952 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - Letters to Psychiatrist (Dr. B), 1952-1953 (Box 2, Folder 49)
      - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Family Correspondence (Box 2)
      - Louchheim, Donald, 1951-1965 (Box 2, Folder 51)
      - Louchheim, Hal, 1950s-1962 (Box 2, Folder 52)
      - Louchheim, Joseph, 1949-1970 (Box 2, Folder 53)
      - Saarinen, Eames, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 54)
      - Saarinen, Eric, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Oversize, Aline Saarinen - General Correspondence, 1960-1963, (See Box 2, F41) (Box 15 (sol))
  - Printed Material, 1947-1977, 1.3:; (Not scanned)
    Subseries consists primarily of clippings, in addition to other printed material such as catalogs and publications, that document aspects of the life and work of Aline and Eero Saarinen.
    - Clippings on Aline Saarinen and Family, 1955-1967 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Clippings on Aline Saarinen as Television Correspondent, 1962-1970, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 57-58)
    - Clippings on Aline Saarinen's Book 5000 Years of Art, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Clippings on Aline Saarinen and Finnish Ambassadorship, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Clippings on Aline Saarinen Receiving Honorary Degree from Russell Sage College, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Clippings on Eero Saarinen, 1953-1967 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Other Printed Material on Eero Saarinen, 1962-1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Publication on Hvittrask, Finland, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, 1940s-1970, 1.4:
    Subseries consists of photographs of Aline Saarinen, Eero Saarinen, Aline and Eero Saarinen together, and various family members, as well as photographs from various trips, photographs of residences, and other photographs. Also found are slides of art and architecture that were likely used in some of Aline's lectures in addition to slides of photographs from a trip to Europe taken by Lily Swann Saarinen and her children, photographs of Sampe, Eames Saarinen, and Aline, and photographs of Hvittrask, Finland (perhaps taken by Eero during his trip with Aline and the children in 1958).